Robert Chambers collection on William Wagner and the History of the Wagner Free Institute of Science, 1798-1980 (bulk 1820-1910) WFIS.90-015
Wagner Free Institute of Science
Robert Chambers collection on William Wagner and the history of the Wagner Free Institute of Science
Bulk, 1820-1910
1798-1980
WFIS.90-015
Wagner Free Institute of Science
2.0 Linear feet 5 containers
Incorporated by William Wagner (1796-1885) in 1855, the Wagner Free Institute of Science is a natural history museum and educational institution in Philadelphia that is dedicated to providing free public education in the sciences. The Robert Chambers collection on William Wagner and the history of the Wagner Free Institute of Science includes material collected by Chambers and contains correspondence; genealogical and family information; documents on William Wagner's early business career with Stephen Girard, the Lennoxville Steam Saw Mill and Snowden and Wagner; Wagner Free Instute of Science financial and operational material; and personal material from Sydney T. Skidmore, a member of the Board. This collection will almost certainly not provide a researcher with all the information needed—instead, this is an excellent starting point. Because these materials were, according to institutional memory, removed from other collections by Robert Chambers and kept close at hand due to their importance, these records will not tell the entire story. However, Chambers apparently thought them to be of particular interest and value and therefore, researchers will benefit greatly from consulting this finding aid. Researchers interested in the life of William Wagner, his early business efforts, Stephen Girard, Joseph Leidy, and the operation of the Wagner Free Institute of Science will find this collection to be of great interest.
Chambers, Robert
Wagner Free Institute of Science.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Related Archival Materials note
Wagner Free Institute of Science: William Wagner European travel journal (89-005); William Wagner personal papers (89-010, 93-004 and 98-051); and William Wagner business papers (89-001).
Historical note
Incorporated by William Wagner (1796-1885) in 1855, the Wagner Free Institute of Science is a natural history museum and educational institution in Philadelphia that is dedicated to providing free public education in the sciences. Indeed, “its free public education courses on science … are the oldest program devoted to free adult education in the United States.” (The First 150 Years, page 1).
Robert Chamber served as the Director of the Wagner Free Institute of Science from 1946 to 1980. During his tenure, he collected and assembled a collection of material regarding William Wagner and the Wagner Free Institute of Science.
William Wagner, “a noted Philadelphia merchant, philanthropist, gentleman scientist, and lifelong collector of natural history specimens,” (The First 150 Years, p. 1) was born in Philadelphia and graduated from the Academy, which later became the University of Pennsylvania, in 1808. He started his career in an apprenticeship in the counting house of Stephen Girard, a Philadelphia financier. As time passed, Wagner’s duties progressed until he was “assigned the position of supercargo and sent overseas to look after Girard’s shipping interests,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 2). He continued working for Girard for seven years, learning from him about both business and philanthropy. Wagner then formed two businesses: a mercantile partnership with Captain Snowden creating his business Snowden & Wagner which existed from 1819 to 1825; and the Lennoxville Steam Saw Mill which existed from 1925 to 1828. By 1940, Wagner “retired from his commercial pursuits,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 2).
Until this time, Wagner’s travels provided him with opportunities to collect specimens and in 1841 and 1842, he travelled to Europe with his wife. During this trip, Wagner continued to collect specimens and visited “principal scientific institutes of the Continent,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 2). Upon his return to Philadelphia, the size of his specimen collection necessitated the building of a wing which he called “The Cabinet” at his home, Elm Grove. In 1847, “believing strongly that education in the sciences should be available to everyone, Wagner began offering free lectures on science at his home,” (The First 150 Years, page 1) using his extensive collection of natural history specimens. By 1855, his home no longer accommodated the number of people interested in his lectures, and he moved the lectures to the Municipal Hall at 13th and Spring Garden Streets and formally established the Wagner Free Institute of Science. Its “program [was] codified in a charter drafted by Wagner, himself,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 2) on May 21, 1855. The existing building which houses the Wagner Free Institute of Science was opened in 1865 and includes an exhibit gallery, classrooms, a library and a lecture hall.
Although, he served as President of the Wagner Free Institute of Science until his death in 1885, he prepared for the future of his Institute and, in 1864, decided to leave his “estate to the charge of a Board of Trustees who would continue to run the institution according to [Wagner’s] original goals,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, pages 3-4). After his death, the Board of Directors appointed Joseph Leidy as director of the academic programs of the Wagner Free Institute of Science. Leidy was “a biologist of international reputation,” (The First 150 Years, page 2) and was serving as Professor of Anatomy at the University of Pennsylvania and President of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. Leidy, who served until his death in 1891, “expanded the programs at the Institute to include a more significant and extensive course of scholarly research,” obtained “some of the most noted scientists and explorers of the age, including Angelo Heilpern, Joseph Willcox and Henry Leffmann for his faculty,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 5), founded, with member of the Board Sydney Skidmore, the Society for the Extension of University Teaching on November 5, 1890; and reorganized the Wagner Free Institute of Science’s Natural History Museum into a systematic display. Leidy’s arrangement remains virtually unaltered to this day.
In 1892, Samuel Wagner, along with several other Philadelphians “appl[ied] for a charter to form the Free Library of Philadelphia,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 6) and The Wagner Free Institute became Branch No. 1 of the Free Library. In 1901, a new wing was built and that housed the Free Library branch until the Columbia Avenue branch opened in 1962.
Samuel Wagner served as President of the Board of Trustees of the Wagner Free Institute from 1885 to 1921 and as President Emeritus from 1921 to 1937. Other administrators of the Wagner include: Thomas Lynch Montgomery, Actuary and Librarian from 1886 to 1903; John Rothermel, Superintendent from 1903 to 1913 and Director from 1914 to 1924; Carl Boyer, Curator from 1924 to 1928 and Director from 1928 to 1945; Robert Chambers, Director from 1945 to 1980; John Graham, Director from 1980 to 1988; Roger Montgomery, Director from 1988 to 1992; and Susan Glassman, Director from 1993.
According to the National Register for Historic Places Registration Form, the Wagner Free Institute of Science is “a nationally significant monument documenting the development of science, education and museums,” (NRHP Registration, Section 8, page 2).
Bibliography:
“The First 150 Years: A Brief History,” author unknown, circa 2008.
National Register of Historic Places Form, 1989.
Scope and Contents note
The Robert Chambers collection on William Wagner and the history of the Wagner Free Institute of Science consists of material collected by Robert Chambers. The collection contains correspondence, genealogical and family information, information on Williiam Wagner’s early business career with Stephen Girard, the Lennoxville Steam Saw Mill, and Snowden and Wagner, financial material, operational material for the Wagner Free Institute of Science, and personal material from Sydney T. Skidmore, a member of the Board.
This collection is arranged in four series: “William Wagner Personal Papers;” “William Wagner Business Papers;” “Skidmore Personal Papers;” and “Wagner Free Institute of Science Records.” Prior to the processing of this collection, Wagner Free Institute of Science staff identified almost all the material in this collection and assigned the material to a series. This intellectual arrangement has been maintained.
The “William Wagner Personal Papers” series contains papers that illustrate Wagner’s interests and background. The series includes genealogical, family and autobiographical material on William Wagner as well as education material from the Philadelphia Academy from which he graduated in 1808. In this series, researchers will find evidence of Wagner’s enduring interests in participation in intellectual societies, books, and the natural sciences. Information regarding Wagner’s marriage to and divorce from Caroline Say Moore and his later marriage to Louisa Binney is also included in the collection. Wagner saved a great deal of memorabilia from his honeymoon in Europe following his marriage to Louisa Binney and spent much of this time in Europe visiting natural science institutions and expanding his collections.
The “William Wagner Business Papers” series includes information on Wagner’s early business affairs: as supercargo for Stephen Girard, dealing mostly with the Schooners Helveticus and Rousseau; as co-owner of Snowden and Wagner; and as co-owner of Lenoxville Steam Saw Mill. Other mentions of ships of note included in the series are: Amelia and Caroline. The bulk of this collection consists of financial records of Wagner’s involvement in shipping.
Included in “The Skidmore Personal Papers” series is information regarding Sydney T. Skidmore and his family. The bulk of this series consists of family correspondence, but of note may be correspondence from S.A. Laurs to Sydney T. Skidmore regarding service in the Civil War. Skidmore’s papers also include Louisa Binney Wagner’s obituary and notes by a John Roberts on William Wagner which were written in 1965.
The “Wagner Free Institute of Science Records” series is divided into seven subseries: “Affiliated Organizations;” “Building Materials;” “Board Records;” “Financial Records;” “Publications;” “Library;” and “Museum.” Again, these subseries were assigned by a Wagner Free Institute of Science staff member prior to the processing of the collection and have been maintained.
Of note within this series is the correspondence which includes writers and recipients such as: R. B. Westbrook; Samuel Wagner; William Wagner; Thomas L. Montgomery; Joseph Willcox; Joseph Leidy; John Rothermel; William H. Dall of the Smithsonian Institute; and Charles Johnson, to name just a few. The topics of this correspondence include the University Extension Program, the Wagner Free Institute of Science building, specimen collecting and exchanges, financial information (including rentals and property issues), the publication of the Transactions, and the Museum at the Wagner Free Institute of Science. Important materials within the series are reports such as the Actuary’s Report; the Librarian’s Report and the Museum Reports, the bulk of these ranging in date from 1899 to 1903.
This collection will almost certainly not provide a researcher with all the information needed—instead, this is an excellent starting point. Because these materials were, according to institutional memory, removed from other collections by Robert Chambers and kept close at hand due to their importance, these records will not tell the entire story. However, Chambers apparently thought them to be of particular interest and value and therefore, researchers will benefit greatly from consulting this finding aid. Researchers interested in the life of William Wagner, his early business efforts, Stephen Girard, Joseph Leidy, and the operation of the Wagner Free Institute of Science will find this collection to be of great interest.
Academy and Charitable School of Philadelphia in the Province of Pennsylvania.; Boyer, Carl; Dall, William Healey, 1845-1927; Free Library of Philadelphia.; Girard, Stephen, 1750-1831; Graham, John; Leidy, Joseph, 1823-189; Lennoxville Steam and Saw Mill.; Montgomery, Thomas Lynch, 1862-; Rothermel, John; Skidmore, Sydney Tuthill, 1844-1928; Snowden & Wagner.; Wagner Free Institute of Science.; Wagner, Caroline Moore Say; Wagner, Louisa Binney, 1814-1898; Wagner, Samuel, 1842-1937; Wagner, William, 1796-1885; Westbrook, Richard B., (Richard Brodhead); Willcox, Joseph; Business records; Correspondence; Estate records; Europe; Family papers; Financial records; Legal documents; Libraries; Natural history libraries; Natural history museums; Philadelphia (Pa.); Reports; Science and technology libraries; Science--Study and teaching; Shipping; Ships--Cargo
- William Wagner personal papers, Series 1
  - Genealogical and family information including John Wagner's description of his children's births, baptism, and deaths and letter from Samuel Wagner to his aunt, 1792-1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Philadelphia Academy Material including two copies of "A charge delivered at a publick commencement, July 30, 1808, to the senior class of the Philadelphia Academy ..." by James Abercrombie (inscribed by the author) and Order of the Commencement in the Philadelphia Academy, 1808 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autobiographical notes and news clippings on the life and career of William Wagner, circa 1829, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Account Books and Catalog of Books arranged by William Wagner, 1813-1827 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of recommendation for membership in societies including the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Ferdinandeums of Innsruck, the Academy of Natural Sciences, and the Sorbonne, 1815-1852 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Receipts, 1817-1838 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Wagner and Caroline Say Moore materials including chronology of 117 S. 11th Street property, ante-nuptial agreement, certificate of divorce, tax receipts, release--heirs of Caroline M. Wagner to William Wagner, suit in equity, and William Wagner vs. Trustees for Caroline Swain, 1824-1890 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - William and Louisa Binney's Wedding Trip Memorabilia, including business cards, letters of introduction (J. Ronaldson to H. English, London, J. Nanovede, Paris, and C. Pratt, Paris and V..F. Kosteletzsey to Dr. Endlichon, Vienna), map of Manchester, broadside of Thames Tunnel, and list of baggage, 1841-1842 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and notes regarding travels during honeymoon (includes notes on Edinburgh, Hamburg, and Copenhagen), 1841-1842 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence regarding appointments, 1841-1843 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorandum of stolen articles from William Wagner's home on Turner's Lane, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence from P.J. Hoffman to William Wagner regarding forwarding a receipt book, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invitations to reception for Ulysses S. Grant and invitations to lectures at the Wagner Free Institute of Science and the Closing Exercises at the Fort Edward Collegiate Institute, 1865-1879 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Descriptions of fossils deposited by J. Willcox, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- William Wagner business papers, Series 2
  - Insurance Books, 1813-1816 and 1911-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence regarding the Helveticus and the Schooner Tom, payment of draft by A. Knockman, entertainments in Charleston, SC from J. Gaeland, and business prospects from William Kennard, 1816-1819 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Port of Philadelphia documents, 1817, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding local markets and Brig Superior from J. Stoney and passage to Port of Charleston, SC from J. Jefferson, 1817-1823 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Instructions from Samuel Wagner to William Wagner when serving as supercargo for Helveticus and Rousseau with miscellaneous private bills from Batavia 1817 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shipping documents, 1817-1832 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Various receipts for timber, lumber, arms and payment of Schooner Amelia's crew, 1817-1840 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Various lists of stores, receipts and customs papers regarding Stephen Girard's ships Helveticus and Rousseau, 1817-1819 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Various records relating to Stephen Girard's ships Helveticus and Rosseau, including lists of cargo purchased, stores, damaged goods and accounts of sales, 1817-1819 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from Thomas Parker to William Wagner regarding imports and exports, 1818-1821 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence including letters from William Wagner to J. Snowden regarding business in North Carolina; letters from D. Crummelin and Sons to William Wagner regarding the state of the Amsterdam market and a print review and import-export list; and letters from J.E. Bellner and Company to William Wagner on business in New Bern, North Carolina and congratulations on engagement to Caroline Say (2 folders), 1818-1823 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Documents relating to the partnership and dissolution of Snowden and Wagner, including some letters of agreement, private bills, extracts from books, lists of assets and debts due, and inventories (four folders), 1820-1826 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Correspondence from J. Snowden to William Wagner updating on business affairs, 1821 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters from William Wagner to Henry Devine of the Lennoxville Steam Saw Mill regarding conducting his lumber and shipping business in North Carolina (four folders), 1828 (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
  - Receipts for a variety of items and services, including rental properties, wages, sundries, furniture, books, clothing, grave digging and coal, 1827-1832 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Records on William Wagner's business in North Carolina including payment receipts for store goods, licenses, articles, payment receipts for crew, bills for lading, and articles and invoices for Lennoxville Steam Saw Mill, 1827-1828 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Financial records relating to business in North Carolina, including information regarding general store, lumber mill, hiring of laborers and Negroes, and shipping goods on the Schooners Amelia, Deborah and Caroline, 1827-1828 (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
  - Schooner Amelia payment receipts, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Taxes, rent receipts and deeds for 11th Street properties (possibly the home of Charlotte Binney), 1829-1844 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Receipt for services for Schooner Amelia, loan agreement between T. Wagner and William Wagner, Charlotte Binney Declaration of Trust and William Wagner Estate, including a list of lease payments on properties, 1829-1845 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - J. Chew Lawsuit, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Shawnee County Tax Sale Certificate, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Skidmore personal papers, Series 3
  - Skidmore family correspondence to and from: D. Miller to Fanny Miller; S.T. Skidmore to A.D. Atkinson; R. and Carrie Rau to Lulu; Mary D. Purvis to Sadie Dewhurst Skidmore; J.B. Humphreys, T.W. Rounds and Company of Providence, RI, to S.T. Skidmore regarding his illness; G.M. Tuthill to S.L. Tuthill regarding family visit; to Fanny Miller from Anna Miller and Caroline Comstock; S.L. Tuthill to Charity Tuthill regarding family; Emma Dickinson to Lou Skidmore; Invitations from B. Mann and P. Mann; Aunt May to Lulu Skidmore while Lulu was visiting her grandmother Louisa Binney Wagner; S.T. Skidmore to Sadie Dewhurst Skidmore regarding wedding and European trip; and Fannie Miller to Sadie Dewhurst Skidmore on S.T. Skidmore's death, 1806-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from S.A. Laurs to S.T. Skidmore regarding service in the Civil War, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letter of recommendation for Sydney T. Skidmore from H.B. Richardson, Amherst College, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mortgage certificate paid by Peter A.D. Widener with deed purchase of same property at 18th and Montgomery by Sadie [Dewhurst] Skidmore, 1879-1887 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sydney T. Skidmore's notes and invitation to reception for Ulysses S. Grant, circa 1879 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Louisa Binney Wagner's obituary, 1898 May 30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - John Roberts' notes on William Wagner, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Wagner Free Institute of Science records, Series 4
  - Affiliated Organizations
    - Correspondence regarding organizations including Drexel Institute of Art, Science and Industry; State of Ohio Board of Library Commissioners; American Library Association; and Free Library of Philadelphia, 1896-1897 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 12th Anniversary of the Philadelphia Mineralogical Club, 1904 October 11 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Building Materials
    - Correspondence of R.B. Westbrook, Henry B. Foulke and Samuel Wagner regarding building repairs and insurance, 1880, 1885-1886 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence regarding estimates for museum cabinets from W.M. Nice, Jr., Mahlon Fulton & Co., Karcher and Rehn Co., and Hale and Kilburn Manufacturing Company, 1892-1900 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Receipts from Robert H. Jacobs, Plumber, Gas and Steam Fitter, and A.W. Farley, Tin Roofing, Heaters and Ranges, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence regarding property issues, 1900 March-May (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence from G. Hewitt to J. Willcox and Harry Brocklehurst regarding rough casting of building and repairs, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Board Records
    - Charter of the Wagner Free Institute of Science in William Wagner's hand and Charter, Deed, and By-Laws of Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art (with handwritten revisions by William Wagner), 1859 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Letters of Joseph Willcox to Mr. Wharton, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Financial Records, 1885-1900 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1885, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Sydney T. Skidmore Reports, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Memos from Thomas Montgomery to Samuel Wagner regarding bills and finances, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Letters from R.B. Westbrook to Thomas Montgomery regarding new books, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Memos from Samuel Wagner regarding specimen and estate transactions, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Postcard from Joseph Leidy to Joseph Willcox, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - G. Cliff's letter regarding acceptance of appointment to Board of Trustees of the Wagner Free Institute of Science, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence regarding attendance at Board Meetings, including letters from Samuel Wagner, Thomas Montgomery and G. Cliff, 1889-1900 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Letters to Thomas Montgomery regarding portraits of Joseph Leidy, R.B. Westbrook and Mr. Baird presented to the Wagner Free Institute of Science, 1900-1901 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Report of the combined Committees on Museum and Library regarding increased facilities for the Free Library at the Wagner Free Institute of Science, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Minutes, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Actuary's Reports, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Committee on Administration Reports, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Actuary's Reports, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Actuary's Report, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Financial Records
    - Receipts and correspondence regarding Rental Property Transactions, 1865, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence regarding Ignatius Lutz's rental, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Plumbing bills, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence from McCartney and Oler regarding Undelivered Warrant, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Treasurer's Account Auditing Report, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Report on vacant properties, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 38)